### Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/ bharadwajakumar (LinkedIn)

## Top Skills

Machine Learning
Natural Language Processing
Algorithms

### Languages

English (Full Professional)
Hindi (Professional Working)
Telugu (Native or Bilingual)
Tamil (Limited Working)
Kannada (Professional Working)

### Certifications

The Challenges of Global Health
Computer Vision Basics
Introduction to Sustainability
Natural Language Processing
Specialization
Foundational Artificial Intelligence

### Honors-Awards

Number of Students Ph. D students guided
Invited Talks

## **Publications**

google scholar link

# Dr. G. Bharadwaja Kumar

Professor at Vellore Institute of Technology & NASSCOM Certified Master Trainer (Associate Analytics)

Chennai

# Summary

Areas of research: Speech and Natural Language Processing, Machine Learning, Deep Learning.

I am passionate about developing resources for Indian Languages in the areas of NLP and Speech. I have developed several applications and resources in the areas of NLP such as "Automatic Text Summarizer for PPT Creation", Indian Language Speech Recognizers, Indian Language parallel corpora etc. I have completed DST young scientist project on "Exploring Better Language Models for Developing LVCSR Systems for Dravidian Languages". I have completed more than hundred courses on Coursera in the areas of data science, machine learning and deep learning.

I was the in charge for curriculum development for the Programs (M.Tech CSE with Specialization in Big Data Analytics, M.Tech Integrated Business Analytics) and SMAC at VIT. I have been invited as a speaker on Data Analytics for more than 100 workshops in Tamilnadu and Andhra Pradesh, Kerala. I am also founder Programme chair at VIT for M.Tech CSE with Specialization in Big Data Analytics.

I have guided four Ph.D already and two more students are pursuing.

I am also NASSCOM certified master trainer for Associate analytics certification.

My google scholar link: https://scholar.google.co.in/citations? user=ppJfQbMAAAAJ&hl=en

# Experience

Vellore Institute of Technology 10 years

Professor

July 2018 - Present (3 years 11 months)

Chennai Area, India

Co-ordinator for Artificial Intelligence Research Group

Associate Professor

June 2012 - June 2018 (6 years 1 month)

Currently I am working on developing Large Vocabulary continuous Speech recognition, Text to Speech, deep learning and big data analytics.

Program Chair for M.tech CSE specilization in Big Data Analytics June 2013 - June 2017 (4 years 1 month)

Chennai Area, India

### AU-KBC RESEARCH CENTRE

Member Research Staff February 2008 - May 2012 (4 years 4 months)

I have worked on developing Tamil, Telugu and Indian English Large Vocabulary Continuous Speech recognition systems at AU-KBC research center.

## Education

University of Hyderabad

Ph.D, Computer Science · (2001 - 2007)